American Dialect Society Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series IV: Electronic Media (Box 1)
Hyacinth
Keswick [Albemarle County]
New Castle
Oak Grove [Westmoreland County]
Oldhams
Remo
Richmond
Salem
Wares Wharf [Essex County]
West Point [King and Queen County]
Weems [Lancaster County]
Wicomico Church
Washington (State)
Grand Coulee Dam
West Virginia
Wisconsin
Wales
West Indies
Appendix C: Informant Names
An asterisk indicates that the name is not in the LC Name Authority File.
Alexander, Melvin L.
Allen, Romeo E.
Alley, Joshua
Alley, M. R., Mrs.
Anderson, Virginia Asbury Gill, Mrs.
Andrews, Emma, Mrs.
Andrews, James
Andrews, Maria
Arendale, Mary
Arthur, Susan
Ashby, Mrs.
Ashton, Sally
Atkins, Elizabeth
Atkinson, Everett C.
Aydelotte, Charles
Aydelotte, Nellie Rich
Baker, Bessie
Baker, Harriet C. C., Mrs.
Baker, Henry
Baldwin, Mr.
Ball, Emma (Falls), Mrs.
Ball, Norman
Barbar, Clarence
Barrows, Edward, Mr.
Barrows, Grace Kilpatrick, Mrs.
Barton, Frank
Bates, Edwin
Baxter, William
Beaumont, George
Bedell, Lee Berton, Mr.
Belknap, Leverett
Bemis, A. A., Dr.
Bennet, Georgiana
Billings, Mr.
Blakeslee, John
Blanchard, Mr.
Blaylock, Mary Frances
Bloch, Bernard, 1907-1965.
Blood, Lawrence
Boardman, Anna, Mrs.
Bostwick, Leonard
Bowen, Otis J.
Boyd, Phoebe (Aunt)
Boynton, William
Brainerd, William H.
Branch, Percy
Branch, Sam
Brandenburg, Edith
Brewer, Frank
Brewster, Ellis W.
Brewster, Lois
Brewster, Spencer H.
Bronson, Joe, Mrs.
Brooks, Muscoe, Mr.
Brooks, Sarah Ashton
Brooks, William Wilson
Brown, Charlie
Brown, Diana
Brown, Frank
Brown, George M.
Brown, George P.
Brown, Katy
Brown, Kenneth
Buford, Cleaton
Buford, Florence
Capers, Lucy
Capers, Paris
Carlton, Elijah B.
Carr, Emily, Mrs.
Carter, J. M., Mr.
Carter, J. M., Mrs.
Carter, James
Carter, John C. C.
Cawley, Frank
Champlin, John R.
Champlin, Sarah, Mrs.
Chapallaz, Marguerite
Chase, Margaret T.
Chesnut, George L.
Clark, Annetta, Miss
Clark, Frank
Clark, Henry
Clark, Ruth
Clarke, S. H.
Coe, Olive
Coffin, Edward F.
Comins, Danforth
Cooke, Alistair, 1908-[2004]
Corn, Ella May
Covell, William King
Covell, William King, Mrs.
Cox, Katherine
Cox, Russell
Crandall, Edward Jarvis
Craw, Rebecca Ellen, Miss
Crawford, A. D.
Crawford, Hattie Blanche, Miss
Crawford, Orlando W.
Crosby, Anne
Crosby, George
Curren, Mary Young, Mrs.
Curtis, Otis
Daddow, Jane E.
Dammell, Ellen, Mrs.
Dana, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, 1881-1950
Davis, Frederick
Dean, E. K.
Demtos, M.
Denham, Grace
Denny, A. I.
Denwaldie, Miss
Desale, Grey
Dodd, Artie Lou
Donelson, William H.
Dorsey, Frank
Dowse, Charles H.
Dudley, Gustavus Garnett
Dwinell, Clarence R.
Dwinell, J. W.
Eastman, Mr.
Eckstorm, Fannie Hardy, 1865-1946
Elwell, Oscar E.
Elwell, Verder Oscar
Emerton, Ephraim
Erving, Henry W.
Fennelly, Isabelle, Mrs.
Fiske, Arthur W.
Fitzherbert, Martha Lunday, Mrs.
Fletcher, Donald
Fletcher, John Gilman
Fletcher, Lucy Rebecca
Folger, Sidney B.
Fox, Lyttleton Jr.
Fraser, D.
French, Batterson
Friesman, Ed
Froback, Wilbur
Fuller, Virginia Van Heusen, Mrs.
Gage, Thomas Hovey
Gaines, David A.
Gaines, David N.
Gardner, Ben
Gardner, Elizabeth F.
Gardner, Ensign
Gardner, Henry
Garland, Mary
Garner, Elrue
Garner, Sarah
George, Lizzie Evelyn E., Mrs.
Gerow, Charles F.
Gibbs, James H.
Gifford, John I., Mrs.
Giles, Richard
Gold, Charles L.
Goodell, Fred H.
Gorden, Mr.
Goslee family
Goslee, Henry C.
Grandgent, C. H.
Grant, David A.
Gray, Tyler W.
Green, George
Gregory, John
Gregory, Leslie
Gregory, Ruth
Grub, Fanny, Mrs.
Guptill, Lutie Martha, Miss
Guptill, Marcus, Mr.
Haddocks, Price
Hagerman, Frank
Hall, Adgielon K., Mr.
Hall, Adgielon K., Mrs.
Hall, Shadrach
Hampden, Walter
Hamson, Jack
Hancock, Beverly
Hancock, Frankie, Miss
Hanley, Miles L.
Hanners, Anna
Hanners, John
Harding, Julia Virginia, Miss
Harlow, A. J., Mrs.
Harlow, Hiram
Harmon, Joe
Harris, Margaret
Harris, Newman
Harris, Newman, Mrs.
Harris, Peyton
Hart, Benjamin
Hastings, I. W., Mr
Hastings, I. W., Mrs.
Hatfield, Margaret
Hayes, Hiram
Hayward, Edwin D., Mr.
Hayward, Mary Ellen, Mrs.
Heath, Emily A., Mrs.
Hersey, Frederick A.
Hill, Allen, Mr.
Hill, Archibald A.
Hill, Clara A. W., Mrs.
Hill, Mr.
Hill, Mrs.
Hinckley, Benjamin
Hinckley, Benjamin Jr.
Hinckley, George
Hinckley, Will
Hobbs, Nelly A., Mrs.
Hock, Louis N.
Hodgdon, Captain
Holland, W. A.
Horton, Henry T.
House, Elmore, Mr.
Howard, Leslie
Howard, Ray, Mrs.
Howe, Charles Raymond
Hubbard, John T.
Hubbard, Richard E.
Humphrey, Chester W.
Johnson, Bob
Jones, Daniel
Jones, Elgin A.
Joyce, James, 1882-1941
Kamman, William F.
Kenyon, H. F., Mrs.
Ketchum, Louise, Miss
Kilpatrick, Sarah, Mrs.
Kimball, William H., Mr.
Kincaid, Julia B. (Nay)
King, Judson
Kroha, Lucy Hoyt
Kurath, Hans, 1891-
Lamb, Adella, Mrs.
Land, Ray, Miss
Lane, Frank (Francis Pie)
Lapham, Dana
Lapham, Harding
Lary, Austin L.
Lary, Austin L., Mrs.
Lathrop, Elisha
Lathrop, Elwood
Laughlin, Robina L., Miss
Lawrence, Andrew
Lawson, George
Leach, Casper L.
Lee, Charles
Lee, Logan
Lee, P., Mrs.
Lee, Robert
Libbey, Mr.
Lindstrom, Dorothea
Lomax, Alan, 1915-
Lomax, John Avery, 1867-1948
Longueil, Ralph
Longworth, Roy
Lowman, Guy Sumner, 1909-1941
Lyford, Harry Lee
Mack, John Averil
Mack, Robert
Mack, Wallace Preston
MacKenzie, Elmer Duncan
Maddocks, Ella, Miss
Maddocks, Mrs.
Magruedan, Mrs.
Mahones, Rule
Marden, Bessie Webb
Marshall, Billy
Marshall, Gordon
Martin, James S.
Matthews, Zachariah Keodirelang
Mawney, John Gardner
McIlvin, Madison Preston
McIntosh, Bristow
McIntyre, Adelia Gindrel, Mrs.
McIntyre, Eldrige
McLean, James O.
Melvin, Howard
Merrill, Richard
Meserve, William H.
Millgate, Mr. M.(?)
Milligan, Hester
Mills, W. R. Jr.
Miner, Lawrence
Moissi, Alexander
Monson, Harry Edgar
Moore, Vernie Royce, Mrs.
Morehead, Addie Lamb, Mrs.
Morehead, Mildred, Mrs.
Morris, Tom
Morris, William
Morse, Elsie (Sargent), Mrs.
Morse, R. G.
Moulton, Ada May Glover, Mrs.
Murphy, John G.
Murray, Belle
Naddeau, Zeline Odibert, Mrs.
Neptune, Joseph
Nichols, Amos, Captain
Nickerson, Sam
Nightingale, Jimmy Percy
Norton, E. R.
Noyes, Joe
Odiorner, William Wallace
Ogelvie, Liz
Orcutt, Charles, Mr.
Page, Arthur
Page, Charles P.
Paige, Alva
Paige, Alva, Mrs.
Paine, Sarah, Mrs.
Palmer, Benjamin F.
Parkhurst, John Henry
Parler, Mary Celestia
Parsons, Ida B., Mrs.
Partridge, Harvey W.
Payne, Alice
Pearson, Fred D.
Pearson, J. Lyman
Peck, Howard
Peck, Howard S.
Peck, Howard S., Mrs.
Perkins, Edwin R.
Perkins, James
Perkins, Katherine (Polly), Miss
Perry, Marion, Miss
Philbrook, Augustus E.
Philbrook, Elizabeth
Philbrook, Grenville
Philbrook, Helen
Philbrook, Lawrence
Pinkham, T. S., Mr.
Pitts, Mr.
Polite, Samuel
Pratt, Frank
Preston, Tom (Uncle)
Quall, Susan A., Mrs.
Quarterman, Wallace
Quinby, Ralph
Raddin, Joseph B.
Reinartz, John L.
Richardson, Grace Carter
Roberts, Mrs.
Robertson, Guy
Robinson, Angie Foster, Mrs.
Robinson, George A.
Robson, Bessie Marden
Rogers, James
Ross, Sarah, Mrs.
Russell, John, Mr.
Russell, T. M.
Sampson, Maggie, Mrs.
Sanborn, John Henry
Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
Savage, Roswell E.
Schofield, Ethel Lord
Scott, Anne
Scott, C. T.
Sennett, Mr.
Seward, Elwood Harris
Short, Alberta Steele
Shurtleff, Clara, Miss
Singleton, Sancho
Sipes, Charlie
Skinner, B. F. (Burrhus Frederic), 1904-
Smith, Prince
Smith, Tom, Captain
Sperloff, Gary
Squires, Levi
Stafford, Dwight B.
Stairs, Allen, Reverend
Steele, Dorothy Elizabeth
Steele, Granville, Mrs.
Steele, Sarah Maria Gould
Stevens, Ashley
Stevens, H. Emagene, Mrs.
Stevens, Leon A.
Stevens, Nellie D.
Stewart, Mrs.
Stiles, Ray
Stillwell, Margaret
Stone, Charles A.
Stone, Charles Jr.
Stone, Elizabeth
Stone, Molly
Stone, Robert L.
Stowell, Ralph
Sturges, Wilbur
Sweetwine, Sackie, Mrs.
Taggett, Ada, Mrs.
Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981
Thompson, Lincoln
Thompson, Susanna Rebecca Wright
Treat, Clara
Treat, Lillian
Trefethen, Fred Ervine, Mr.
Troop, Sam
Tucker, Herman G.
Tucker, Wilson
Tutt, Hannah
Tuttle, Charles H.
Tyler, Miss
Tyson, Rosie Francis Wimstead, Mrs.
Vaughn, Morton D.
Vincent, Charles W.
Walker, Balaam
Walters, Margaret
Ware, John Faulconer, Mrs.
Warner, Herbert E.
Warren, Harry
Warren, Harry, Mrs.
Warwick, Gertie
Warwick, Jim
Warwick, Mary, Mrs.
Washburn, Edgar W.
Washburn, Ruth Ella (Blake)
Washington, Lawrence Augustine, Mr.
Washington, Scotia
Watts, Howard, Mr.
Weathern, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin)
Weathern, Edna Jennie
Weeden, Arthur, Mrs.
Wells, Floyd
Welsh, Frederick
White, Davy
Whitehill, Alexander J.
Whitehill, Martin G. W.
Wicker, Billy
Wiggin, James
Wigginton, James
Williams, Mary Snow, Mrs.
Williams, R. H. (Robert Haden)
Wilson, Ernest
Winn, Andrew
Wise, C. M.
Wise, Margaret Ruth
Wise, Mr.
Wise, Paul
Witt, J. S., Mr.
Witt, J. S., Mrs.
Witt, Ronald
Woodfin, Annie, Mrs.
York, Abbie
Young, George William
Appendix D: Glossary of Abbreviations, Selected Names, and Terms Found in the Collection
Interviewers and recordists were usually identified by initials or other abbreviations on the discs or disc sleeves. Persons writing comments on the disc sleeves also identified themselves with initials. Information about the recording situation written by the recordist was sometimes included in these notes, often in abbreviated form. The following list includes these abbreviations and their meaning when known. In addition, some abbreviations and terminology used in the collection materials and in articles about the collection are listed here.
A. C. - Alternating current (type of current used to make the recording)
ADS Collection - The American Dialect Society Collection
AFC - American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
A. H. - Archibald Hill, fieldworker
A. R. M. (or ARM) - probably a recordist (see AFS 25057-25077, 25080, 25096, 25098, 25100-25108
B. B. - Bernard Bloch, fieldworker and Assistant Editor for LANE
CAE - Center for American English
CAL - Center for Applied Linguistics
c. m. - condenser microphone or carbon microphone? Probably not a person's initials. Found on discs AFS 25077, 25080, where ARM is the recordist. So "c.m." is probably a technical note, not initials
Caffee - Unknown recordist; this may be Nathaniel M. Caffee (Nathaniel Montier Caffee), who published articles in American Speech
DARE - Dictionary of American Regional English
D. C. - Direct current (type of current used to make the recording)
Diamond - recording needle type
G. L. (or GL) - Guy S. Lowman Jr., fieldworker
Garwick - Walter C. Garwick, a collector
"Hanley discs (or disks)" - frequently used to refer to all the discs in the American Dialect Society Collection, or sometimes just to the disc copies which Miles Hanley retained for research
"Hanley tapes" - tape copies of Miles Hanley's disc copies of the American Dialect Society Collection made by Frederic Cassidy in 1972 (now housed at the Center for American English).
Hard - may refer to type of microphone, or type of disc
HY - Miles L. Hanley, fieldworker and associate editor of LANE
H. K. (or HK) - Hans Kurath, editor of LANE
J. D. - Unknown interviewer and/or recordist [possibly Jane E. Daddow, a student of Hans Kurath]
LANE - Linguistic Atlas of New England
M/B/RS - Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound division, Library of Congress
M. C. (or MC) - Marguerite Chapallaz, fieldworker.
"Platters" - Raven I. McDavid's term for the aluminum recording discs, used by others connected with the collection. This term is found in the collection correspondence, and presentation events materials.
R. L. S. (or RLS) - Robert L. Stone, recordist
Sapphire - recording needle type
"Saturnalia" - Raven I. McDavid used this term for any winter festivities. In particular, he used it to refer to the American Dialect Society meetings and to the events surrounding the presentation of the collection to the Library of Congress. This term is found in the collection correspondence.
Soft - may refer to type of microphone, type of disc, or disc treatment.
Appendix E: Selected Bibliography
The following is a partial bibliography of references related to the Linguistic Atlas Project. A more extensive list of materials produced prior to 1939 appears in the Handbook of the Linguistic Geography of New England (Kurath, et al. 1939), including a "Bibliography of Linguistic Geography" (pages 54-61) and a "Bibliography of New England History" (pages 105-121).
Angle, Burr, and Richard Venezky. "A Report on the Materials in the Hanley English Language Collections at the University of Wisconsin." Unpublished manuscript, Department of English, University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1968.
Blair, Walter, and Raven I. McDavid Jr., eds. The Mirth of a Nation: America's Great Dialect Humor. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1939.
Cassidy, Frederic Gomes. The ADS Dictionary – How Soon? University: University of Alabama Press, 1964.
Davis, Alva Leroy, Raven I. McDavid Jr. and Virginia G. McDavid, eds. A Compilation of the Work Sheets of the Linguistic Atlas of the United States and Canada and Associated Projects. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1969.
–––. A Compilation of the Work Sheets of the Linguistic Atlas of the United States and Canada and Associated Projects. Second edition, Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 1969.
Davis, Lawrence M. ed. Studies in Linguistics in Honor of Raven I. McDavid Jr. University: University of Alabama Press, 1972.
"The Dialect Society and the Dialect Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 2 (1930): 65-78.
Duckert, Audrey R. The Linguistic Atlas of New England, Revisited. Publication of the American Dialect Society, no. 39 (1964).
Kurath, Hans. "Report of the Conference on a Linguistic Atlas of the United States and Canada." Linguistic Society of America Bulletin, no. 4 (September 1929): 20-47.
–––. A Word Geography of the Eastern United States. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1949.
–––. Studies in Area Linguistics. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1972.
Kurath, Hans, and Raven I. McDavid Jr. The Pronunciation of English in the Atlantic States. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1961.
Kurath, Hans, with Miles L. Hanley, Bernard Bloch, Guy S. Lowman Jr. and Marcus L. Hansen. Linguistic Atlas of New England. 2 volumes, Providence, RI: Brown University, 1939-1941. Reprint edition, 3 volumes, New York: AMS Press, 1972.
Kurath, Hans, with Marcus L. Hansen, Bernard Bloch and Julia Bloch. Handbook of the Linguistic Geography of New England. Providence, RI: Brown University, 1939. Second edition with a new introduction, word-index, and inventory of LANE maps and worksheets by Audrey R. Duckert, and a reverse index of LANE maps to worksheets by Raven I. McDavid Jr. New York: AMS Press, 1973.
McDavid, Raven Ioor. Dialects in Culture: Essays in General Dialectology. Edited by William A. Kretzchmar Jr. with James B. McMillan, et al. University: University of Alabama Press, 1979.
–––. Folk Speech. Cassette recording of lecture. Deland, FL: Everett/Edwards, 1979.
–––. Varieties of American English: Essays by Raven I. McDavid Jr. Selected and introduced by Anwar S. Dil. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1980.
McDavid, Raven I., and Audrey R. Duckert, eds. Lexicography in English: International Conference on Lexicography in English, New York, 1972. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences 211. New York: New York Academy of Sciences, 1973.
McDavid, Raven I., with Raymond K. O'Cain, George T. Dorrill, and Guy S. Lowman. Linguistic Atlas of the Middle and South Atlantic States. Vol. 1. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1980.
"Per Aspera." Dialect Notes 6, part 18 (1939): 709-710.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 4 (1932): 235-236.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 5 (1932): 281-282.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 6 (1933): 335.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 7 (1933): 365-368.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 8 (1934): 391-392.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 10 (1935): 449-452.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 11 (1935): 481-485.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, parts 12-13 (1936): 513-516.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, part 15 (1937): 622-624.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas." Dialect Notes 6, parts 16-17 (1938): 625-627.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas and Plans for the Future Work of the Dialect Society." Dialect Notes 6, part 3 (1931): 91-98.
"Progress of the Linguistic Atlas and Proposals for the Continuation of the Work." Dialect Notes 6, part 9 (1934): 417-419.
"A Report on the Proposed Investigations of Southern Speech." Dialect Notes 6, part 9 (1934): 420-424.
"Seminar on the English Language in America." Dialect Notes 6, part 11 (1935): 486-487.
Turner, Lorenzo Dow. Notes on the Sounds and Vocabulary of Gullah. Publication of the American Dialect Society, no. 3, May 1945.
–––. Africanisms in the Gullah Dialect. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press, 1949. Reprint edition, New York, NY: Arno Press, 1969. Reprint edition with a new foreword by David DeCamp, Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1974.
Waterman, Margaret. "The Hanley Tapes." Unpublished manuscript by the Associate Editor of the Dictionary of American Regional English. The University of Wisconsin, 1974.